Guide to the George Reber Wieland Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
George Reber Wieland papers
1889-1953
MS 750
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.75
The papers include professional and family correspondence, periodicals and pamphlets, books annotated by George Reber Wieland and scientific and personal photographs. The professional correspondence deals with his scientific expeditions and with negotiations on his proposed gift to the United States of a tract of land in South Dakota known as the "Fossil Cycad National Monument."
Wieland, G. R. (George Reber), 1865-1953
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mary Wieland, 1975; and Saskatchewan Museum of Natural History, 1985.
Biographical / Historical
George Reber Wieland was born in Boalsburg, Pennsylvania, on January 24, 1865, the son of Washington Frederick Wieland and Margaret Reber. Having received his B.S. degree from Pennsylvania State college in 1893, he studied at the University of Gottingen, the University of Pennsylvania, and Yale University, from which he received his Ph.D. in 1900. He married Elda Kristina Anderson of Nykoping, Sweden, in 1891.
Wieland entered Yale intending to study vertebrate paleontology, but during the summer of 1897 while aiding O. C. Marsh in collecting in South Dakota, he met the paleobotanist Lester Ward. Ward had made a collection of cycadeoid trunks in the Black Hills of South Dakota in 1893, and it was through Ward's encouragement and Marsh's collecting that Wieland's scientific interest in these fossil trunks flourished. It is principally through Wieland's efforts that Yale accumulated a collection of 1,000 specimens which is considered to be the world's largest collection of cycadeoids.
Wieland was an internationally recognized paleobotanist noted for his research on the fossils of cycads. He held several academic appointments at Yale: lecturer in paleobotany, 1906-1920; research assistant in paleobotany, 1924-1935; and Sterling Fellow in botany, 1928-1929. He took part in several expeditions in North and South America and in Europe, and he made two important discoveries in the Black Hills of South Dakota: a petrified forest of cycads and a skeleton of Archelon, the largest marine turtle known to science. The skeleton is on permanent display in Yale's Peabody Museum of Natural History.
Wieland took title as a homesteader to a 360-acre tract in the Black Hills. He gave it to the United States in 1922 for the purpose of establishing the Fossil Cycad National Monument, but he became involved in a public quarrel over this project with Harold Ickes, Roosevelt's Secretary of the Interior. After the attack on Pearl Harbor, plans to develop the monument were postponed indefinitely.
As well as being one of the first scientists to be designated a research associate of the Carnegie Institute, Wieland was also the recipient of a gold medal from Archduke Rainer of Austria and a medal for his dedicatory address at the Capellini Museum at Bologna.
Until his retirement in the 1940s, Wieland remained at Yale as a research associate. During his academic stay, he wrote his important two volumes on American Fossil Cycads (1906, 1916). Wieland died in 1953.
Scope and Contents
The papers represented in this collection, which were donated by Wieland's daughter in 1975, represent only a fraction of a larger body of papers which have apparently perished.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into five series: Series I. Correspondence. Series II. Writings. Series III. Biographical and Personal Materials. Series IV. Printed Materials. Series V. Photographs and Prints.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
The general correspondence in Series I is available in digital form through the Yale University Library Digital Collections. Links to the digital form are provided in the collection description.
Botany; Cycads, Fossil; Ferns, fossil; Paleobotany; Paleontology; Science; Black Hills (S.D. and Wyo.); Botanists; Paleobotanists; Paleontologists; Wieland, G. R. (George Reber), 1865-1953; Yale University -- Faculty
- Correspondence, 1889-1950s; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Correspondence, consists of General correspondence, the majority of which is of a professional nature. The fields of paleobotany and paleontology are discussed at greatest length with additional references made to other fields of science. Among the more interesting correspondence is that which deals with expeditions in which Wieland took part. There are at least two references, in letters written to Wieland, to a revolution in Mexico (18 February 1914 and 11 May 1916). These comments were made apparently in reply to letters of Wieland's which are not in the collection. (It appears that he made few copies of his own letters). The professional correspondence discusses scientific discoveries made in diverse areas such as South Dakota, Kansas, Texas, Mexico and Argentina.
  The Cycad National Monument correspondence consists of letters written in reply to Wieland's suggestion that there be a museum built at the Cycad National Monument. The correspondence is routine but does include the autographs of Harry Truman, senator from Missouri and Hugo L. Black, senator from Alabama as well as many other senators, congressmen and officials of the Department of the Interior.
  The Family correspondence deals primarily with difficulties encountered by Wieland in his efforts to straighten out the title to the Wieland family farm.
  - General correspondence, 1889-1906 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General correspondence, 1907-1910 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General correspondence, 1911-1914 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General correspondence, 1916-1925 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General correspondence, 1926-1931 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - General correspondence, 1932-1935 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - General correspondence, 1936-1939 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - General correspondence, 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - General correspondence, 1943-1953 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Cycad National Monument correspondence, 1936-1937 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Postcards, circa 1889-1950s (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Posthumous letters, post 1953 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - General correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Family and related correspondence, 1923-1925 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Family and related correspondence, 1926-1930 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Family and related correspondence, 1931-1933 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Family and related correspondence, 1934-1940 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Family and related correspondence, 1941-1949 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Family and related correspondence; newspaper clippings, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Wieland family genealogical correspondence, circa 1889-1950s (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Wieland family genealogical materials, circa 1889-1950s (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Financial records, 1903-1946 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Stock transaction records, 1918-1943 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Writings, 1896-1910, undated; Series II
  Series II. Writings, consists of original manuscripts of several articles and the book Araucarian Forests. There are also reprints of several articles and a book, American Fossil Cycads. This series includes three expedition notebooks which may be of value to a researcher but do not appear to be very complete or extensive. Notes made on envelopes and pieces of paper are also found in this series.
  - Codaitean Wood from the Indiana Black, by Marian G. Elkins and G. R. Wieland (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Manuscripts of scientific papers, by G. R. Wieland (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Araucarian Forests, by G. R. Wieland (Box 3, Folder 26-27)
  - American Fossil Cycads (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Review of Wieland's The Cerro Cuadrado Petrified Forest, by W. C. Darrah (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Reprints of scientific monographs by Wieland - I (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Reprints of scientific monographs by Wieland - II (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Harriet Martineau's American visit, by G. R. Wieland (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Notebook of the 20th Geological Excursion, 1898 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Scientific notebook, 1898-1909 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Scientific notebook, 1909-1910 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Notes and fragments (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Notes on lectures on fossil vertebrates given by Edward Drinker Cope at the University of Pennsylvania, 1896-1897 (Box 5, Folder 36a)
- Biographical and personal materials, Series III
  Series III, Biographical and Personal Materials, consists of newspaper clippings, obituaries, an article in the Alumni Weekly as well as some invitations, etc.
  - Biographical and personal materials (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Memorabilia (Box 6, Folder 38)
- Printed materials, Series IV
  Series IV, Printed Materials, consists of periodicals, pamphlets, and books in which Wieland made notes.
  - The Yale Collections (notes by Wieland) (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Sigma IX Quarterly (notes by Wieland) (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Miscellaneous printed matter [notes by Wieland] (Box 6, Folder 41-42)
  - Bulletin of the American Association of University Professors (notes by Wieland) (Box 6, Folder 43)
- Photographs and prints, Series V
  Series V, Photographs and Prints, consists of photographs of family members, an eclipse of the sun, fossils, dinosaurs' bones, etc. Some of these may be of scientific value.
  There are some prints of historical figures in whom Wieland was interested and reproductions of illustrations for scientific writings which were probably published.
  - Assorted personal and scientific photographs, prints and reproductions (Box 7, Folder 44)
  - Oversize photographs (Box 8)